a minute. Maybe this morning it may take
a little bit longer for people to join
on in. Um so, uh good morning everybody.
Um just uh we're letting people in from
the lobby. Um just let people know. It
seems like we are having in various
parts of the state some bandwidth
issues. So if we freeze or anything like
that, uh apologize. It is actually part
of why I do not have my camera on right
now. We want to try to preserve that
bandwidth as much as possible. Um this
meeting is being recorded. So as usual,
please remember uh to keep language
appropriate for um for a video because
we do post these up on our website um so
that they are available to everybody. Um
and with that in mind, uh it is this is
the uh research and continuous
improvement committee with Dan Jennings
as the chair. Uh I'm Domerlo with the
New Mexico Department of Health. I'm the
director for the center for medical
cannabis and psilocybin. Um, and with
that, I turn the meeting over to you,
Dan. And thank you.
>> Thank you very much, Tom. I appreciate
that. And welcome everybody. I really
appreciate your time again on this
Friday morning to come to the research
and continues improvement committee. And
I um really excited today for our
presentations that we have from our
intercession workg group and of course
from our guest presenter that we'll have
a little bit later on. Uh so in this
time, this is usually the time that we
like to go through and make
introductions and say hi to everybody.
And uh if we would be possible, I'd love
for uh Dominic to go ahead and introduce
his team from the Department of Health.
And in the process of doing that,
everybody else that's on the call, we
would love to have you introduce
yourself as well. So for you to be able
to introduce yourself, just raise your
hand using the team's hand feature. And
at the end of the department of health
introductions and announcements, then
we'll call on you uh in order to have
your introduction as well.
And so now if you might or anybody from
the department of health team introduce
who from do is here today.
Sorry. Sorry on that, Dan. I I uh I was
actually speaking, but because I had uh
turned my mic on mute, nobody was
hearing me, and you didn't know because
I also don't have the camera on. So, my
apologies. Um, okay. So, we do have uh
and and uh uh we'll go ahead and I'll
actually start with other board members
because I do see some of the other board
members. Seems like Dominic is having
audio issues or am I the only one that's
having audio issues?
>> Sorry, Dan. Can you hear me?
>> Abs. Yeah, I can hear you.
>> So, okay. So, um I'll I'll go on ahead.
Um so, uh we'll go ahead and I'll start
with Department of Health and then we'll
go to the other folks. Um and uh so
today we do have and I'm just going to
go in order um and uh and introduce
them. We have um and we introduced him
yesterday. We have a new intern that who
just started with us. Uh his name is
Vicente Royal and so Vicente well
welcome to the team and glad that you
were able to join today. Um we have
Kathy Ojiri who is our project manager
uh and especially with regard to our IT
program. We have Adrien Estrada and
Katie Fry who are two of our health
educators and who have been many of you
will recognize them from other meetings
because uh as we get things moving
forward with our educational programs
for the public they will be instrumental
in helping with that. Uh we have Raymond
Gyos who is one of our analysts and who
helps us with some of the research
gathering data and helping to put some
uh different items together. We have
Jorge Gonzalez who is our medical
psilocybin program manager. Uh and uh we
have Brenda Martinez who is our center
deputy director. We have Johnny Musher
who is our management analyst and is
instrumental in helping us set up all of
these meetings um and keeping me on
track quite frankly. Um, and we have
Leslie Peterson who is our compliance
officer for the psilocybin program and
Cyrus Routman who is our environmental
scientist for the medical psilocybin
program. And the two of them along with
Jorge are going to be very busy in the
next several months especially as we
start having uh applications coming in
for cultivators, laboratories, and when
we get to that point uh all of the
different providers, healing centers,
etc. Um, and then we have uh Dr. Robert
Truckner who is our c center's medical
director. And so I think I got everybody
from the department on. If I miss
somebody, my apologies. Um, and now at
this point, um, Jorge, I'm not sure who
is doing the mute unmute for attendees,
but uh, if we can move on to introducing
allowing attendees to introduce
themselves.
>> We will do. Uh, Leslie.
Yep, I'm on it.
>> Thank you.
>> Welcome.
>> Sky, you can go ahead and introduce
yourself.
>> Okay. Oh, okay. Uh, good morning
everyone. I'm blessed to be here once
again. I'm Sky Rivers. I'm with the
Santa Fe Reporter and I'm sitting in.
Thank you so much.
>> Um, James Brown, go ahead.
>> Morning, Dan. Morning everyone and hope
is having a blessed day. Again, James
Brown. I'm here to help out. just so
excited to be part of this and uh
anything that we can do and and move
this forward. Again, have a great day
everybody.
>> Don Moser.
>> Yes. Hi, good morning. Uh my name is Don
Moser. I live in Las Vegas, New Mexico.
And I have no affiliation, just a really
strong interest in this program. And I'm
very glad to be here. Thank you.
Danielle Leonard.
Danielle, you can introduce yourself.
You have your hand up.
Okay. Um, you can go ahead and uh enter
your information on the chat. Thanks for
being here.
Hannah Rose.
>> Hi, good morning. My name is Hana Rose.
I'm a BSW student um here in Silver
City, New Mexico
and first generation Quendetta and just
glad to be here. Um staying in the loop
with everything. Appreciate all the hard
work going into everything. Thank you
all so much.
>> Brenda, go ahead.
Brenda Burgard.
>> There we go. Can you hear me now?
>> Yes, Brenda. Thank you.
>> Oh, okay. Hi everyone. Good morning on
this uh very steamy July day. My name is
Brenda Burgard. I am chair of training
and education for uh the psilocybin
medical program. and thank you for your
attendance here today and I hope this
meeting is uh really informative for
everybody. Thank you
>> Gregory.
[clears throat]
>> Good morning. How are How's everyone?
>> Good morning.
>> My name Yeah, my name is Gregory Evans.
I'm an independent micologist and
researcher.
Um,
I do have an affiliation. I am
affiliated with a company called Ignite
Synergy. We're working on an agentic
system of care that allows people to
track long-term outcomes um, and report
back to their care teams.
I'm in Santa Fe and I'm a little behind
this morning.
Good morning, Morning
everybody and I know that there are some
intros in the chat and so I'll read
those in. Uh Danielle, just one just
because I know that this usually does
happen sometimes if you're not able to
open the mic. Sometimes it may be good
to just to leave the teams meeting and
see if you can rejoin the team meeting.
That sometimes fixes that. And of
course, you can always use the drop down
next to the microphone and just make
sure that your microphone is there
selected there as well. And I believe
that we have centerboard
I've enabled your mic.
There we go. I apologize. Good morning,
everybody. Good to be with you. I'm
State Senator Jeff Steinborn. I am I was
a lead author of the Medical Psilocybin
Act and really excited to listen in this
morning and uh yeah, excited to join
your committee this morning, Dan. So
thanks everybody for joining in.
>> Thank you sir for being here.
And in the chat we have uh Kate Hawk her
introduction. Uh Kate Hawk from Santa Fe
40 years MAPS member trauma therapist
harm reduction currently researching
psychedelics and end of life care. Chris
Kuski is the advisory board member
veteran and community advocate. Hanife
Nayo is Santa Fe PMH Alliance. Ellen
Shimmels from Psych Mental Health nurse
practitioner from Albuquerque. Danielle
Leonard. Hi, I'm Danielle Leonard. I'm a
psychotherapist living in Santa Fe and
research peak and mystical experiences
with NMHU. I'm on work group two and
three for the RACI. And uh or just made
a comment in the chat about how in case
your microphone's not being able to be
unmuted. And Roman Politzky. I'm Roman
Politis, licensed psychologist and
faculty at Emory University. Honored to
be a guest presenter for today's meeting
and uh [clears throat] appreciate you
being here. If there is anybody else
that hasn't uh made their introduction,
please feel free to drop that into the
chat and we'll read that into the record
as we go. Um like I said, super happy
for you all to be here. this is uh a
really great opportunity and actually
this just kind of leads right into our
our next part of our presentations. So I
would love to give an introduction to
Roman Pitzky for being here today. Uh
Dr. Pitzky is the director of research
projects for Emery Spiritual Health and
Research Psychologist at the Emory
University School of Medicine where he
works with uh Emory Center for
Psychedelics and Spirituality. Today he
will be speaking with us on his work
around safety monitoring and adverse
experiences and psychedelic assisted
therapy. Dr. Bitzky has developed a
leading assessment framework for
identifying measuring and assessing
adverse experience or adverse events in
these therapies focusing on how skilled
interpersonal support and careful
monitoring can both enhance therapeutic
potential and reduce harm. His research
has been published in the journal of the
American Medical Association Psychiatry
and other leading journals and he has
been a central voice in building a
stronger safety net for this emerging
field. He holds a PhD in clinical
psychology from the University of
Arizona and a masters of divinity from
Harvard University. Please join me in
welcoming Dr. Roman Pitzky. And Dr.
Pollitzky, just so you know, I do have
your presentation here. I'm happy to
share. Um, but I'll stop my sharing in
case you're able to. And if just one
thing, since you are in presenter mode,
there is a leave button up there in case
you do have to leave. Hit that one. Not
the end event. Otherwise, it's kind of
like the self-destruct button here. So,
[laughter]
so I appreciate you being here. Go ahead
and give it a shot if you can share. And
if you can't, like I said, I've got it
up, too.
>> Thank you so much. Uh, let me see. Um,
uh,
can people see?
>> Awesome.
>> Wonderful. Well, it's it it has just
been such a pleasure to connect with
this group and I'm such a big fan of
everything that y'all are doing. Um,
right. So, uh, I'm going to talk a
little bit fast because I know that, uh,
this there's a a pretty packed agenda
for today and I don't want to overt tax
my time. Um and uh so
just
right this is who I am and this is uh
where we are. Um so I just want to give
a very brief shout out to the center
that I work in. Uh I'm an assistant
professor at Emory uh in the department
of psychiatry. Uh and I'm also faculty
at Emory spiritual health which is our
chapency service across 12 different
hospitals in our hospital system. Um the
other place where I work is the Emory
Center for Psychedelics and
Spirituality. And here's a brief
snapshot. Actually, our faculty has now
expanded uh beyond the small group. And
it's it's a really um I think one of the
strengths that really infuses the work
I'll be talking about is the very deep
and interdicciplinary expertise uh from
Emory and other centers that has really
come to inform it. Um a little bit about
me. So my work really falls into at
least in the context of psychedelics
into three buckets. Um the first buckets
bucket is uh really trying to understand
the spiritual, existential, religious
and theological dimensions of
psychedelic care. I spent a lot of time
trying to understand how that works. The
other bucket is uh thinking about the
psychotherapies that we pair together
with psychedelic treatments and how do
we optimize and best understand those
therapies. And the last and probably
fastest growing bucket that my work
falls into is uh harm reduction, risk
reduction uh and safety uh
understanding, measuring and addressing
adverse effects. and that uh and that's
really what I'll be talking about today
primarily, although I'm also happy to to
talk about any of these other topics. Um
so maybe a little bit of a first uh kind
of context setting. Uh for those here
who've lived through the the high tide
of the drug war, you're probably
familiar with some of this material. uh
the this is your brain on drugs ads and
uh you know give me one good reason why
I shouldn't use LSD and we can give you
46 which refers to this uh really
specious claim that uh LSD can damage
chromosomes there's no evidence for that
uh incidentally but um this is not that
talk um
rather I think it's important to have a
good and realistic perspective on the
benefits and potential enhance
enhancements to well-being as well as
potential as a treatment for a lot of
conditions that psychedelics bring as
well as their uh real risk profile so
that we can mitigate the exist the risks
that do exist and um I do have some
pretty good news to share. Um I use the
the term psychedelic uh uh in a specific
way throughout. Uh so I refer to classic
psych classical psychedelics like uh you
know the 5HT2A receptor agonists. Um but
I also include compounds that are
sometimes popularly thought of as
psychedelics uh uh such as MDMA or
ketamine. I know that that is a uh
sometimes a divisive uh definition, but
I'll just leave that there. But
basically the good news is that
psychedelics are generally considered to
be safe. Um there's this wonderful now
classic paper u by Matt Johnson and
colleagues from 2018 that really lists
uh psilocybin containing mushrooms all
the way at the bottom end of a
distribution of potential risk carrying
compounds. Um and I think that that is
largely correct. Um, we also have
evidence that comes in from clinical
trial adverse event monitoring and I
will tend to rely on these definitions
unless stated otherwise throughout this
discussion. So, um, when I say adverse
event, it's any abnormal sign, symptom,
or disease temporally associated with a
subject's participation in research
whether or not it's considered related
to the subject's participation in
research. So what that means is that if
somebody has a automobile collision uh
after taking part in a psilocybin uh um
uh trial that should probably get logged
because we don't yet know whether there
are any sort of larger um um ambient
effects or or uh extensive effects that
might increase propensity towards such
things. Um a serious adverse event are
very concerning risks to health and
safety. Um we typically log these by
using medical dictionaries like the
medra. Um medra is an expansive
dictionary contains 27 system organ
classes and over 76,000 lower level
terms to document adverse events in
treatments. So there is a very robust uh
science base for looking at adverse
event events and treatments. Um in
psychedelics again the good news is that
serious adverse events are reported at
rather low rates. Um two years ago a
sort of a glowing uh brief from JAMAMA
found that psilocybin's adverse effects
mostly resolve within 2 days.
Um and we have data from some phase 2
trials uh and uh now phase three trials
uh we're we're starting to see coming
out. Um but at least with psilocybin so
uh one trial from raison and colleagues
found 76% of participants reported some
adverse events but serious adverse
events in only 8% of participants. Uh
goodwin and colleagues found 84% rate of
adverse event with serious adverse
events among 10% and something notable
here is that there was a report of
increased suicidality among some of the
patients in that trial.
So that is generally the good news. Uh
now here is the rest of the news and
here's kind of where where a lot of what
I do comes in. Um adverse events are
reported at low rates but there is good
reason to suspect that this is because
of uh systematic uh underounting. Um,
one reason is that uh the majority of uh
of psychedelic trials and research has
relied on passive monitoring, which
means that we wait for participants to
tell us about specific adverse events
rather than probing for specific uh
specific negative uh impacts or adverse
events.
uh they've typically suffered from low
frequency of adverse event assessment
and uh and not much followup in terms of
adverse event assessment. There is a
hyperfocus on the acute dosing
experience. So what happens when
somebody is actually under the influence
of psilocybin
um rather than the the followon effects
which is kind of ironic because when we
talk about the potential of psilocybin
we don't talk about you know how amazing
the experience itself is going to be
although that's certainly a part of it
we often think about the ripples and
repercussions of that one single
treatment in a person's life. So if
we're looking for the benefits in the
days, weeks, and months following
dosing, we should probably also be
looking for potential risks in those
time periods as well.
They've also suffered from non-sistatic
assessments. So there is no systematized
way that we tend to evaluate adverse
events in psychedelic trials. We rely on
systems like the CTCE, which is not a
it's not an instrument. it is more of a
dictionary and system for logging
adverse events.
Finally, we have uh a restricted set of
criteria. Uh and what that means is
again many of the benefits that we see
from psychedelics tend to be in these
you know pretty um
uh pretty broad domains like existential
wholeness, meaning making um uh
spiritual and transpersonal experiences.
But we don't really even have the
language to document potential ill
effects in those domains. We also
typically pair psychedelics with some
kind of an interpersonal therapeutic
component, but we don't log those
adverse events either. Um a review by uh
Hinkle and colleagues, this is uh the
John's Hopkins team found that since
2005, so this is in the current um what
what we what some call the psychedelic
renaissance, this is in the modern era
of psychedelics, less than a quarter of
studies systematically monitored and
reported adverse events.
So going beyond uh clinical trials, we
can there's a little bit more signal now
about rates as as they occur in the
world. Um and what we have and there's
just a couple of these studies coming up
now. So one uh one study that took an
epidemiological approach um found that
so again really good news 59 to 88%
uh depending on which sample you looked
at reported no challenging experiences.
Uh among those with challenging
experiences
uh [snorts]
uh between 6.4 4 and 9% reported
functional impairment lasting over a day
and 1.3% reported impairment lasting
over a year. Uh 2.6% of those samples
sought medical, psychiatric
uh or psychological assistance after
their worst experience. So, if we're
going to do some back of the envelope
math here, um according to the latest
data from Rocky Mountain PO uh poison
and drug safety, uh about 20 12 million
people have used psychedelics in the
last year. So, we take that 2.6% 6%
number of people who sought medical,
psychiatric or psychological assistance
after their worst experience. And we
multiply that by 26%
uh by 12 million and you get 312,000
seeking further support. The 1.3% number
of people with difficulties or
impairment lasting over a year, you get
156,000 people. Um so very small numbers
but they add up when you start to scale
uh psychedelics and it's important that
we have some kind of answers for these
folks. Um uh we also know that poison
control center calls for psychedelics
have tripled between 2018 and 2022 and
emergency department visits and
hospitalizations uh for hallucinogens
have increased approximately 50% uh
between uh 2016 and 2022.
So, we are in a situation here. Uh, I
hear this metaphor a lot in the sort of
in the psychedelic world where like
we're building the air, we're building
the plane while it's up in the air. Um,
and my response is sometimes like, well,
we do know that the best place to build
a plane is probably on the ground. Uh,
but here we are. Uh, we've got a plane,
it's up in the air, and we're trying to
encourage flourishing with therapeutic
psilocybin while reducing harm, reducing
risk. Um, I don't mean reducing harm in
the sense that these compounds are
inherently harmful in any way, but
reducing the frequency or capacity for
harm to occur.
So, I want to make a distinction right
away as I talk about this between uh
challenging experience uh or an acute
adverse event on one hand and uh
psychedelic related challenges or
adverse effects on the other hand. And I
think this is a pretty important
distinction. So when we talk about an
acute adverse event or a challenging
experience, we're talking about the
actual dosing period when somebody is
under the influence of the of the
psilocybin. An adverse effect or a
psychedelic related challenge is
something that would occur in the days,
weeks or months after the dosing. Uh
challenging experiences can be very
distressing at dosing.
uh adverse effects. These may or may not
be distressing at dosing. So, somebody
can have a perfectly wonderful
experience and then experience insomnia
in the weeks afterwards.
Uh a challenging experience or adverse
event can involve major concerns,
injuries or harms um uh during the
actual event. Uh and here in the adverse
effects I'm talking about distress or
impairment that's really there after the
psychedelic effects wear off. Um now a
challenging experience may or may not
have any negative impact and I've met
many people and we have these people in
our studies who have a very challenging
experience a very difficult uh dosing
session but then really report a lot of
benefit from those difficulties. And I
think it's really important to uh to
respect and honor those narratives. Uh I
think there's something real going on
here. Um when we're talking about an
adverse effect, we really are just
restricting ourselves to something that
has some kind of a negative impact on a
person's life. Um
so I've I've mentioned that benefits and
harms can be associated with challenging
experiences. Um, so an important an
[clears throat] important wrinkle here
is that, you know, you can have and I
think we get into this sort of binary uh
narrative a lot in in the psychedelic u
adverse effects research world that is
it an adverse effect or is it really a
benefit that hasn't sort of uh uh
manifested yet. And I think we we don't
need to think of things as either
adverse event or adverse effects or um
or benefit. It can't be it has to be one
or the other. Um you can absolutely
experience negative impacts and you
might experience growth at the same
time. Um and a person can experience
real and legitimate growth and
improvement from their symptoms. But
that might also involve some negative
impacts for them as well. And I think
that this is the case for a lot of our
therapies. If we think about our
chemotherapies, these can have real
negative impacts or uh adverse effects
that we need to monitor and help people
with and they can also be life-saving at
the same time.
So our tasks and by our I mean our
research group and my lab at Emory uh
are to are first of all detecting
adverse events and adverse effects in
psilocybin research but also and this is
why I'm so excited to be speaking to
this group in the implementation of uh
psychedelic therapies in the healthcare
systems.
Uh another task and this is related is
understanding adverse effect phenotypes
for primary and secondary prevention. So
understanding what is the nature of
adverse effects? Are they all created
equal? Are there subtypes? Are some more
hazardous than others? And are there
preventive strategies that are
especially useful or treatment
strategies that can help people to
recover from certain types of adverse
effects?
And finally, uh, I've become
increasingly, uh, interested in
developing monitoring systems that work
and that are not sort of siloed across
the many different contexts in which we
see psychedelic therapies, uh, studied
and implemented.
So for I'll talk about the first one the
most um, and this is adverse event
measurement for trials. But we have been
actually moving into the implementation
uh world with this because that's
actually how we designed this uh method
in the first place. Uh two years ago we
published a paper on this. So framework
for adverse uh for assessment of adverse
events occurring in psychedelic assisted
therapies.
And the background for this is that we
already have pretty good
pharmarmacological
type adverse event assessment in
psychedelics. And this is the kind of
adverse event sets that we see in the
published trials. So this is Goodwin and
colleagues in 2022 and they report all
of these different adverse events
occurring in their trials. And you might
notice though that these are all uh all
events that occur during dosing. Right?
That's the first thing I think that's
important to uh to be alert to. Um uh
and they rely on systems like Medra that
have this extensive vocabulary.
However, there are a whole other uh
there's an a whole other item set or
criteria set for adverse events that
again where we look for benefits from uh
from psychedelics where we know we might
have a signal because people are
reporting these informally uh in the
trials and also because they're uh
sometimes just built into the therapies
themselves. So, we developed a uh a
system that comes with a measure for
monitoring all of these. I'm not going
to go through all of the tiny type here,
but I will walk you through what this
figure represents, and it's in our
paper. Um,
essentially what we did was we reviewed
all of the possible instruments
that could be used to measure a list of
adverse event criteria that a group that
a panel of experts and stakeholders came
up with as uh adverse events of of
interest in in psychedelics.
And so these these criteria are grouped
in these sets. Uh we actually don't know
yet empirically whether that grouping is
going to cluster them in this way or
whether they're going to uh the clusters
will will look slightly different in the
world. And that's part of uh part of the
work that we're doing now. Um, but
you'll notice these uh across the top
row in each box are letters and these
represent the uh the different measures
that exist for for assessing uh each
each possible adverse event type and the
X's uh represent whether that measure
actually captures uh or is designed to
capture that adverse event. So that's
that's what you're seeing with the grids
and the X's. Uh something that I want to
point out that I think stood out to us
right away is that the instrument that
had the most coverage of any uh of all
of the adverse event criteria that we
were looking at was actually an
instrument that was designed to capture
adverse events occurring in um
meditationbased uh interventions. And I
think that that reflects some of what
we're seeing is that the impacts of uh
of psychedelics can be uh can be broader
than just physiological impact. They
they impact more than just mood, more
than just um uh these sort of
psychiatric endpoints, but they can
reach into uh metacognitive,
existential, and even spiritual domains.
And so it's important to assess the
relevant criteria.
I'll just talk about a few of these uh
for the interest of time. Um and the
first one that I'll mention is the
psychosspiritual domain. Um this is a
formulation that I think uh people
who've spent some time with the
psychedelic research world will probably
be familiar with that there's a sort of
there are these spiritual and
existential impacts and there is sort of
an open question about the extent to
which these uh these spiritual or
existential effects are actually driving
some of the therapeutic benefits. Um the
basically the short version of the
answer is we don't have enough data to
know yet. But what I became interested
in along with my colleagues
we we know that if there are benefits to
spirituality people tend to do better.
But what happens if uh people experience
spiritual difficulties? So if somebody
takes uh psilocybin uh and you know
they're expecting to have this this
beautiful spiritual experience they're
uh to to to meet their creator and
instead what they experience is really
just a whole lot of nothing or worse,
right? And they come away with it
profoundly from it profoundly
disappointed or uh have a crisis of
faith. um that is that's going to be an
added difficulty that they're now
dealing with after the psilocybin
treatment and uh we've we've been
looking at this in a couple of uh
different studies and papers as well as
uh as colleagues around the world. Um,
if you're interested in this, I really
encourage folks to find Rachel
Peterson's essay, um, a theological
reckoning with bad trips, which was part
published in the Harvard Divinity
Bulletin, uh, where she describes her
own experience of, uh, of difficulty uh,
after taking psilocybin as part of a
clinical trial.
So the kinds of domains that we're
looking at here include existential
distress um death anxiety which is not
um like being afraid that one is in
imminent danger but distress about being
mortal um spiritual struggles within
oneself but also spiritual struggles
with one's community of faith. If you
are part of a religious community and
you rely on that for your well-being,
for your social capital, for your uh
community and suddenly there's a rift
with that community after a psychedelic
treatment that could undermine a
person's resilience and we want to be
able to uh to monitor for that. Uh, of
course, religious or spiritual abuse or
imposition are important to monitor and
unfortunately we know that these happen
although more often in the sort of in
the gray or underground space. Um,
the other set of adverse effects I want
to talk about are psychotherapy related
harms. Uh there was a wonderful uh essay
published about 3 years ago about how um
studying harms is key to improving
psychedelic therapies. And what the
authors say is it would be unimaginable
for clinical trials using a combination
of two drugs to only examine or regulate
one of the two components. However, this
is the norm in psychedelic research in
which the psychological support is
neither systematized nor evaluated as in
traditional psychotherapy research and I
don't think we're actually doing a very
good job evaluating it in traditional
psychotherapy research but uh but she
they do have a point um so adverse we
know that adverse event assessment that
relies only on pharmarmacologically
derived criteria
underestimates adverse effects related
to behavioral, lifestyle, and
psychological therapies uh routinely.
And we also know that adverse effects do
occur at regular rates in everyday
run-of-the-mill psychotherapies. So
about 3 to 7% of patients in uh standard
psychotherapies experience adverse
effects and 7 to 15% in treatments for
substance use disorders.
And if we're uh and this is important to
note because psychedelics are also used
for substance use disorders sometimes.
Um so the kinds of adverse effects we're
monitoring are uh strain in the
therapeutic relationship, excessive
dependence on the therapist, which
unfortunately we've seen happen with
psychedelics. Um uh therapist abuse or
exploitation, feelings of abandonment,
uh of course any kind of a boundary
violation or transgression. And this is
uh this is actually something that that
came up in a conversation with Rob, but
uh loss of confidence toward
interventions. I think this is something
that's especially important to watch for
insight in insilocybin therapies when
these can be thought of by patients as a
treatment of last resort sometimes that
this is the you know I've tried I've
tried Prozac I've tried psychotherapy
I've tried all these things nothing has
helped me but I think psilocybin can and
if that person comes away without
improvement is that person coming away
with a sense that nothing can help them
now so we this is something that we want
to avoid. And this is something that
every team that I know that has been
doing psilocybin research has worked
very hard to avoid that framing. And yet
they tell me, you know, it's really hard
to hard to escape that a patient might
have that view. Anyway,
so the last domain that I want to
mention and I think this might be of
particular interest to this group is uh
socioultural uh harms, socioultural
adverse events. So um generally speaking
and I'm I'm relying on some work by by
Dennis Went uh Joseph Gan and Donna
Nagata um that primarily they work with
First Nations and Native American
communities and they talk about you know
how do you uh monitor for cultural harms
uh in these communities and first they
notice well you know we actually don't
have any evidence uh of harms there's no
denial of care or or early dropout um no
uh increase in intensive care, no
critical misdiagnosis that we're seeing,
but the absence of evidence doesn't mean
an evidence of absence. And largely,
it's the same story that I've mentioned
with psychedelics. We're just not
assessing any of these things. There's
lack of assessment or research. There's
lack of any frameworks in psychiatry for
assessing these uh negative cultural
impacts. And there is an absence of any
uh and yet there is long-standing
evidence that these harms do occur. So
if you haven't read these books, I
really recommend them. They're not easy
reads. Uh medical apartheid, uh the
protest, psychosis, bad medicine, um are
all important just to sort of uh
familiarize ourselves with the ongoing
and certainly historic uh cultural harms
that can be perpetrated in uh in
standard therapies.
Um and we do have some emerging evidence
in uh the psychedelic research that
patients and stakeholders have reported
cultural harms. So I I think it's it's
probably inappropriate to make this
connection of absence of evidence to
evidence of absence and instead we can
recognize that harm itself is a social
construct.
uh psychotherapy may be inherently
ethnosentric
and that strategies for collecting
evidence of harm should be integrated
with a social justice agenda. So I'm
quoting uh Lent and colleagues. Uh but
the upshot here uh however you interpret
that last part, I think it's important
to recognize that our cultures give us
uh the language that we use to
understand what is helpful and what is
harmful. And so it's important to be
sensitive to how uh these therapies can
have cultural impacts as well. So the
kinds of adverse events that we're
talking about include adverse change in
worldview
uh experience of cultural invalidation
uh increased stigma
uh and uh dis uh things like distress
associated with being a member of a
minoritized identity.
So we have taken this framework out into
the world. We're currently collecting
data in I should say gosh um
I've lost count of the number of
clinical trials uh but there's a number
of clinical trials where we're
collecting data on uh uh using this
measure and also we're collecting it in
naturalistic settings. So this is data
from a prospective sample of people
taking psilocybin out in the world and
what we found is that every single
criteria that we assessed at least one
person reported worsening.
Uh again these are largely people I want
to emphasize who have who reported
improvement in benefit from taking
psilocybin. So you can have both
happening at the same time, worsening in
some domains in the context of also
general improvement and that there are
some domains where rates of worsening
were such that we think it's it's worth
uh looking paying closer attention maybe
offering people more resources. Uh
reexperiencing the psychedelic effects.
This is a known uh effect. Increased
isolation and loneliness. Uh distressing
change in values. So people talk about
things like ontological shock. um strain
in one's relationships uh uh decreased
libido was a bit of a surprise to us. Um
but uh uh yeah just just on the whole I
think evidence is coming through these
are you know this isn't something that
constitutes an emergency by any means
but that these uh adverse effects do
occur uh at regular rates out in the
world.
So there are currently two instruments
that uh that do this kind of
measurement. One is uh comes out of
Switzerland. Uh it's the Swiss
psychedelic side effects inventory. It
includes 32 items. Um and then there's
the instrument that I'm describing here
which includes 54 items. Um and uh I
want to make a I want to be very clear.
So this instrument is uh the Swiss
instrument is published and they
validated with a sample of I think about
150 people. We're doing a much more
careful validation process I think um
where we will have thousands of people
in our sample before we can claim any
validation. And that is the work that's
happening now. That's why it's being
used in all these different clinical
trials across multiple continents. Um
and we're gathering all of these data.
So I'm going to start to wrap up uh but
I just want to kind of briefly mention
the work that we're doing in these two
other areas. One is uh understanding the
phenotypes for primary and secondary
prevention. So understanding what is the
nature of uh post psychedelic
challenges. uh do they are are there
certain typologies and are there ways
that we can offer treatments uh uh to
address difficulties that are
particularly um uh particularly serious.
So we are currently uh conducting
something called the post psychedelic
challenges study. Um you can uh visit
the study website
psychedelicchallenges.org.
Um it's a study that includes uh 800
participants. uh it's an enriched sample
uh with post psychedelic challenges. We
are following 400 of these people uh
with current and recent difficulties for
one year in order to understand
prospectively the time course of these
challenges. Um and we're also doing some
ambulatory assessment as well. This is
actually a comparator study. So we have
a comparator here. Remember I mentioned
that the other best instrument for
capturing the most of these domains came
out of meditation. uh trials. So our
comparator group are 800 people
experiencing meditation related
difficulties and that way we can
disentangle the pharmacological effects
or the the effects that are specific to
the uh to the compounds uh in the
psychedelics.
Um just a little bit about uh
eligibility um recruiting in the US,
Canada and Australia, Europe is coming
soon. if you uh if you would care to
share about this, we would certainly be
grateful. The last piece I'll mention is
about monitoring systems. So the we're
working on a project called Syshare. Um
right now the data landscape is very
fractured. We have all of these
different data sets, all of these
different studies that are collecting uh
safety and risk data. Uh on the left
hand are all of the psychedelic uh
related projects and on the right hand
are already existing public data sets
that capture data that are likely very
relevant to us but they all exist in
their own little siloed microcosms. And
what we're trying to do is to address
that bulcanization by bringing them
together. Um unfortunately these are
just the ones that we know of. The
reality is probably very much like this
where there are dozens of untapped data
resources that could be integrated into
a rob into a robust monitoring uh
framework and that's some of what we're
working on.
So um
I want to thank the folks here. I want
to thank uh the funders for this
research. I'm going to stop the share.
Please uh feel free to reach out and uh
and contact me uh if any of this sparked
your interest and and I'm happy to
answer any questions, of course. Uh
>> thank you. Thank you so much, Dr. Biski.
I appreciate that. And that was what I
was hop
uh you would be willing. I really
appreciate your time because if you do
have some time, I'm sure that the
audience would love to be able to ask
some questions, but I want to call out a
few things. I really wanted to
appreciate that work that you talked
about that the study is not just the
medicine itself, but it's the
integration that goes along with it and
it's important to know that we're we're
looking for the events in this and it's
not just an either or. It's that kind of
both and it's the negative and the
positive effects of this and you kind of
have to have one to have the other as
well to have an effective treatment
therapy. So, like I said, big thank you
for bringing that insight to us. So,
while I'm kind of letting everybody
raise their hand, um I would love for
y'all if you do have questions, uh
things that you would like to ask. This
is this is an exciting opportunity to
have Dr. Pollsky with us. And I wanted
to thank Danielle so much for helping to
set this up. Um she has been doing so
much with the work groups along with uh
uh James Brown, Gregory Evans and Linda
Fatimi, Danielle Denali Wilson, Eileen
Brewer and Victoria.
So anybody that would love to ask some
questions, please make sure your hand is
raised and we'll get to call on you here
as well. While you're doing that, I'll
read some comments from the chat in
here. Uh James Brown, so excited to have
you here. Gregory Evans shared a link
for Peterson's piece, The Theological
Reckoning with Matt Trips. Kate Hawk,
thanks for this enlightening
presentation. Um, and then Dr. Polliski
dropped his uh email into the chat. Sky
Rivers, brilliant presentation. And
Danielle Leonard on that last slide. Is
there a scoring or coding structure that
supports monitoring trends over time?
And have you thought about what a
program level dashboard or periodic
review of AE data might look like? I'm
working on how our program would monitor
these findings on an ongoing basis, not
just case by case.
Yes. Uh the the the short answer
[laughter] is yes. And I can share all
of that. So we have a scoring system and
an approach that's uh uh uh one that's
useful for clinical trials more so
probably and one that's more useful for
public monitoring. Um we're already
working with um Oregon's uh open uh
group that is uh sort of we're uh being
integrated into into their uh uh monitor
actually with with with the other with
the with the 800 person enriched sample.
Um but there is a um yeah the short
version is yes there's a framework and
yes there the there are ways to uh to
monitor these findings on an ongoing
basis.
Great. Thank you. Yeah, the uh we had uh
last month um open uh muis
and came and their presentation was
fantastic. So, it was great to hear that
y'all are working together on that as
well. There's great integration between
those. Uh and we do have a question from
Gregory Evans.
Yeah, I've try been trying to
[clears throat] avoid this just being me
asking a bunch of questions for an hour,
but how much time do you have?
>> You got three minutes on your question
and then we'll jump to somebody else. We
can jump back. [clears throat]
>> No, I really want to hear what everybody
else is thinking here. Um,
I have a short list, but I think um,
starting with uh, just the overall how
this
how your work could
have a mutual benefit with the New
Mexico program. What do you see look it
looking like for
us to [snorts] fold this type of
framework into our outcomes and research
data and
considering the scale kind of mirroring
open I'm really hoping that we are able
to surpass that
um capacity of their data set um but to
get but what does it look like for wild
data where where [clears throat] it's
not in a controlled study and then
beyond that leveraging like ongoing year
5year plus data for um integration level
tracking with alignment practice the
container outside of the experience all
that.
>> So I think that this is the this is the
main aim of what we're doing right is to
is to is to make that possible. Um,
so I I think that there's a lot of
reason not to just assess adverse events
after the treatment. Uh, because a lot
of what we're talking about is worsening
from baseline. So, you know, a person
might say, well, gee, I feel really
anxious now, but maybe they felt really
anxious uh before they took the
psilocybin. And so, um, we we need
baselines. Uh so uh my sense is you know
of the again there's there's there's the
other measure uh which is the Swiss
instrument. It's 32 items but each one
has to be answered three times. You have
to say you know the severity the
relatedness. This is 54 items which I
think can make some people kind of uh a
little wary. it doesn't take all that
long to to answer because most of these
people scan through them and they say
okay doesn't apply doesn't apply doesn't
oh I am having some of this right um so
my suggestion would be at least two time
points one at intake and I think it's
really good for people to even be aware
of what's happen it could be it could
inform the intake process and some of
the trials we work with have used it in
that way um and and then you get to
monitor
rates of worsening. Then what that
allows you to do at a public health
level is to reduce risk. You can then
test out safer administrations, better
uh contexts. You know, we have all of
these sort of questions that I think
can't be answered with clinical trials
like does the psychotherapy matter? We
had a study published I think in in in
one of the JAMAMA journals uh about how
it turns out the amount of psychotherapy
doesn't matter. Well, the number of
sessions ranged from like I I I don't
want to misquote. I know we're being
reported, but it was like it was under
10, you know, and so there's no real way
to assess the marginal benefit of
additional therapy when you don't have a
very wide range at all. But here, I
think you will start to see the benefits
of therapy, the benefits of skilled
practitioners. and that I think we will
will respond will correspond with a
lower rate of worsening lower rate of
adverse events in these key criteria. So
that's one part of the answer. Just a
very other short version is everybody I
think is interested in including us in a
screener and in order to have a screener
you need some data about what we're
screening for.
>> Um so so I think in 5 years we will have
a good screener. Um, right now I think
that really the best and really it's a I
I think it's a fairly timeefficient way
is just to kind of give a short list of
things a person can check off and then
then you know
>> yeah I think the the [clears throat]
just leveraging on that like defining
baseline is something that I don't think
that we spend enough time um really
getting into finding the whole human who
they are like I want [laughter] man I
want like gut veagal tone before you
take before you ingest anything like
there's like enthod
tests that are being developed that
define your propensity for different
types of chemicals um like are your HD2A
receptors masked by another like
emotional stress [laughter] like um but
getting [clears throat] that baseline
and then and then measuring alignment of
care provider Right? So, like I'm the
atheist in the room. I wouldn't do well
with somebody who's trying to push a
specific dogmatic practice on me in a
therapeutic sense. And making sure that
like I feel aligned as well as my
provider feels the alignment as well as
the rest of the care team sees that
alignment, right? and measuring the
outcome of that in a harm reduction
space like it it it's it's it's stuff
that's so that feels so complicated and
so far away. But I I'm with you in that
in that vision of like in 5 years if we
start doing this in this container and
we start getting real data on the board,
we can hopefully start to measure some
of those things that feel outside of our
understanding and language.
Yeah, you're you called it out with that
harm reduction mentality in public
health and I think that we have a really
great opportunity in New Mexico to use
this model for exactly that because it
really encompasses quite a bit more than
just like we're starting a psilocybin
program. This is more than that. This is
something that we can really affectuate
a lot of change. Um I'm going to pick up
James next and then I'm going to read
into uh Danielle's question to you as
well after James's question. So, James,
go ahead. And then we'll go to Kate.
>> Your mic's enabled. James,
>> I know he's been waiting a little bit,
so he might have stepped away. Um,
James, when I'll watch your mic and see
it get unmuted. Uh, in the meantime, I
will go. Oh, there you go. Thank you. I
knew if I saw
>> Oh, there we go. Sorry. Uh, Dr. Blinsky,
thank you so much uh for coming here
today and sharing. Um we are so excited
to have you. I can't express that
enough, sir. Um you know, one of the
things I wanted to touch on is, you
know, the the part of challenging versus
adverse. I think we really in New Mexico
have an opportunity in a medical model
to really focus in on harm reduction in
those areas.
And I think that you have brought up so
many good points and in your studies and
research that we've read and and based
some of our previous thoughts and and
currently are doing that with um you
know one of my things is my question
today was with these people that are
admitted right because I always I'm the
pharmacist in the group I always like to
focus on that 300,000 100,000 who the
one person in my world you know and and
with those people were those people that
were admitted because We're seeing more
and more here, right? We're seeing that
huge uptick since 2012, right? And I
work in the ER and I'm seeing these
people come in daily and some of it is
cannabis. Some of these hyper
lucinogenic issues are to cannabis.
Cannabis is in the literature. It's
causing a lot of these, you know,
hypermesis type of issues. And was that
data that you saw was was that just
general psychedelics in general? Did
they just include all of them or was
their stratification breakdown that says
oh no they were on MDMA no they were on
iOS psilocybin they were on you know hia
Iwasa or whatever it was you know was
that bro was that part of the research
or was it just more of a general bucket
do you mean the the the sort of I uh I
think I'll say epidemiological type
studies I guess the the research coming
in from from Colorado is is
epidemiological um so do you mean do you
mean that
Yes, sir. Yeah, that Can you explain
that a little bit more? I love that
stuff.
>> Let me let me think. And you might
actually I mean that's another group to
consider having [laughter]
having come in and uh um I I I don't
recall actually. Uh so so I think it's
it's it's worth drilling down. I know
that in a lot of these samples they
initially people weren't asking and
people have started asking in their
studies. So for example in our enriched
in in our enriched sample one thing I
can speak about with confidence is work
that we've done ourselves. Um so in our
own uh work with with the enriched
sample of participants who have all had
post psychedelic difficulties. Again if
you've just had a challenging experience
you don't qualify for our study. It has
to include some degree of difficulty
after the effects have worn off. We do
assess for co-use and I will say that
co-use is a part of the picture for sure
but it's not the only part of the
picture right so there are and and and
you pointed out cannabis I think there's
a lot of researchers now who are
increasingly paying attention to so the
potential for example for cannabis to be
the real driver for uh psychosis risk uh
because there actually is a mechanism
there right uh and even though these
compounds are have been referred to as
psychotimedic, right? Um there there
there's a more tenuous uh connection
between uh psychedelics and psychos,
which doesn't mean it's not there,
right? It's just there's a um so so I
think psychosis is definitely one to
watch for. Um uh psychosis, sorry,
cannabis is one to watch for. Uh um but
then there there are other um other
domains. This is one of the reasons we
want a phen phenotype. There are
probably certain subtypes of um of
adverse effects that are more
susceptible to to certain kinds of
co-use.
I don't know if that helps.
>> Thank you. It really does. And that's
why I was bringing up the phenotype
issue with that because I think that
because there's so many different
species, right? There's so many
different things that we're going to be
able to do here um that will interact
with polyarm pharmacy. poly substance is
a big thing with some of these issues
that we're seeing I think in these more
serious you know not not challenging
events but more of the serious adverse
events and I think we you know when we
dial up a little bit more we have more
data more data points and I'm so happy
you're saying that because that'll drive
drive so many things for us um and again
thank you so much sir I appreciate you
right there and this is Danielle's
question from the chat I'd like to pick
up on Rob's question about patient
patients who see this as their last hope
and then don't respond. Roman, your
treatment confidence items mean we can
now detect that worsening which raises
the then what question once we can see
it what happens next both clinically for
that individual and at the program level
feeding back into how we set
expectations frame consent and prepare
patients.
>> So I I think that there's two two
answers to that uh to that question. One
is, you know, how do we frame this? We
can start framing this now. We know it's
an issue. We've seen it in our in our
trials. Um, we we also see it in
underground care. Um,
uh,
to me, and may I I may differ from
others in this room, I think the sooner
we can get if we're talking about a
clinical treatment, right? If we're
hanging out a shingle and saying this
will help you with your depression or
your trauma or whatnot, right? The
sooner we can get to a model that is
just part of the community mental health
infrastructure, the better. And that way
we don't have to exceptionalize. You
know, these are remarkable treatments.
They have a lot of potential. And I
think we we can develop better language
and we can really learn a lot from some
of these clinical trial teams to say,
you know, I have a lot of I think this
could really help you, right? Building
that confidence. And if it doesn't,
there's a couple of other things that we
can try,
you know, uh
so we want to inspire hope, right? We we
definitely want to inspire hope, but we
but we also um uh with the patient who
has come out of this, you know, I think
that then we're, you know, after any
treatment that has failed a patient, you
know, there's a skillful clinical way of
dealing. And by the way, we can study
these as well, right? But uh you know uh
there's going to be some grief
as a this is again why I think
psychotherapy is so important ju just
getting to a clinical monitoring
infusion clinic kind of approach is
probably not the system that we're ready
for yet maybe we'll never really that
that might never be the optimal system
right but um when a patient comes out
and gosh you know I just
I don't know if anything can help me now
that's where the therapist comes in and
can process that grief, can think about
options, can, you know, situate it
within the the broader therapeutic
framework that they're already uh using.
I think that we could really stand to
integrate psychedelic therapies into the
context of ongoing mental health
treatment instead of having it be a sort
of a uh a sort of a special service. Um
we can also think about tiered models,
right? And that's where again I think
adverse event assessment can be really
important, right? Where you notice that
there are certain flags that come up and
we're doing research in Colorado right
now actually that is what the the main
focus there is to identify early warning
signs that somebody might not do so
well. And if those early warning signs
pop up, let's get them into a higher uh
into higher tiered uh support. Um and
that way we can simultaneously think
about things like scaling, right?
without providing, you know, the
Cadillac version of the treatment for
absolutely everybody who might not need
it, right? Um but also, uh really be
able to show up for those people who do
need it. So, so that's the, you know,
the what next. The other piece is um
we're we're uh this year we're opening a
small clinic at Emory. I know John's
Hopkins also has a clinic um uh to treat
uh enduring difficulties or adverse
effects after psychedelics when people
present with that as their main problem.
Uh there are no validated empirically
validated treatments for this right now.
Period. Right? They're not even
recognized. You know, you people it's
it's hard to know even how to like there
there are some DSM diagnosis you would
use to build but it's um that's not part
of our lexicon yet. And so I think as
time moves forward with some of these
especially high-risisk phenotypes, it
could be useful to think about okay well
there are treatment models that we can
uh that we can support these folks with.
At present I think if we can pick up on
particular domains of distress there are
existing treatment models that can
address that distress. So if somebody's
coming out uh in our enriched sample,
what we're seeing the most is mood and
anxiety symptoms, right? And so we have
therapies for mood and anxiety symptoms.
We might want to be able to give an easy
on-ramp to those therapies for people
with those struggles.
>> Yeah, thanks for clarifying that because
that is a big thing is that this is not
necessarily the silver bullet that
solves what it is, but it does bring up
a lot of things that may have been
repressed and then now it's like now
what do we do with it? And so it really
isn't even that last resort kind of
thing. It is just anything that we're
dealing with and then getting that
person connected up with ongoing
integrations and therapies and such. Um
I'm going to let Kate be our next uh uh
question. And again uh thank you very
much Dr. Pisky for putting your email in
the chat if there was anybody else that
was interested in in asking questions
offline. Uh Kate, go ahead. Let's ask
your question.
>> Good morning. uh to say where I'm coming
from. This is from about 10 years on the
maps integration list online. So all
kinds of people reached out uh mostly
underground or ceremonial experiences
that they'd had and uh were still
wanting some support and you know with
difficulties or opportunities. But um
what stood out from all of these
experiences, you know, beyond all the
people who just had a rough spot, but
they were growing and they got through
it, was situations where their family,
especially wives or sometimes now
ex-wives. Uh other people had issues
with what they were going through which
may have just been you know some
experience that was temporarily less
than stable but um was then really as uh
exacerbated by you know oh we have to
take your kids away or you know end
ending up in a divorce. So, I'm just
wondering like some of these things
maybe you could spot uh ahead of time
that there were relationship issues if
you were looking at that and some of
them maybe not. Um, so I'm just
wondering how your research captures
that and and what we might be able to
do.
>> Yeah. Well, this kind of goes back to u
and and yeah, first of all, thanks for
your for your work in that area for a
while. I think it's uh for many people
it was it was uh sort of lonely work for
a while because not a lot of people were
there to address it uh to address these
issues when they came up. Um
uh so I
this is why the implementation context I
think is so important. Um, the way that
I think about a therapy is the way that
it finally lands with a patient, which
means that the implementation context is
a part of the therapy unless you until
you're able to to to modify it, right?
And so, um,
many of the domains that we're
assessing, they do check about that
context, right? So, we do assess for
relationship strain. We do assess for
strain with one's community. Uh and uh
because
just like you, we we've seen this
repeatedly. Um in our Colorado study, uh
we're actually assessing for this. We're
doing something pretty amazing. We're
getting people to carry and I hope I'm
not I'm not speaking too long. It's a
but it's it's a neat uh bit of
information. Um we're getting people to
carry around these passive recording
devices that just record audio for 30
seconds once every 12 minutes. So you're
getting uh n 95% of the day is private,
but you get a representative acoustic
sample of a person's day. And what that
lets us really get to two things. One is
people in surveys will often say, "Oh my
gosh, psychedelics have made me a better
person, a great leader, a you know,
wonderful husband, father, you know,
whatever, right? Is that true?" Right?
Can we actually empirically observe?
That's a very hard question to answer.
with this we can because we're actually
observing people's interactions in their
daily environments. But the other thing
that we're able to test now is their
actual context that they're coming back
home to. And we have all of these again
things that uh it didn't take
psychedelics to find out. So we know
that certain family dynamics predispose
patients to a greater rate of relapse.
hostility, criticism, emotional
overinvolvement predict higher rates of
relapse for uh for psychosis, for
substance use disorders, you know, and
um and so so disruption to the family uh
system that comes up after psychedelics
might also be uh cause challenges,
right? Um so I think that that the home
environment is crucial, right? Um at
present, right? I think that it's
something that we have to take into
account because it's part of the
implementation context. So, um
we can we can identify this on the
adverse event side by actually picking
up on greater relationship strain uh by
picking up on uh um uh breaks with one's
community. And that's something that
we're already doing. But on the decision
about how to best present this treatment
to somebody, I think it's really, as
you're saying, right, it's important to
ask, well, how would your family feel
about this,
right? Um, how does your, oh, you're
part of a religious community? And they
think that any, you know, that they've
got drug war uh sort of language and
they think if you've taken psilocybin,
you know, you've gone and ruined your
life forever, right? Well, maybe let's
get one of those maybe let's get your
your your pastor into the therapy room,
right? This is like my my my ideal
world, right? Let's get them in. Let's
all have a conversation about how this
is something that could really help you
with your depression and that everybody
here, you know, is we're not your drug
dealers. We're your we're your
therapists and uh there's uh this is
part of of of a treatment setting. Um,
so, so I think
I I might have strayed a little bit in
my answer off of your your the center of
your question, but I hope this addresses
some of it.
>> That's that's very helpful. Yeah, I
think the point is we've so been so
focused on here's the patient, here's
these symptoms we want to reduce and not
looking at the whole thing. And so even
in current um whole mushroom, you know,
FDA research, it's not considered like
what are these people going back home to
after their PTSD? Uh one mushroom and
minimal uh support. So thank you.
>> And I I I'll say two more things. Um,
one is just something to really that I
that I think is really important for the
states where there is going to be more
use is how many people are visiting you
to take to take psilocybin and what
happens when they come back home, right?
Uh, and and whether they they have
resources over there. Um, and uh the
other is we don't have to reinvent
therapies to think about these things.
If you think about about uh uh pediatric
care, right? We know that if we're going
to do mental health treatment for for
for kiddos, right? We want to know what
their home situation is like. We want to
know what their parents are like. We
want to know if their parents are
supportive, right? So, so this isn't
like brand new a brand new thing that we
have to think about.
>> Thank you very much, K, for that
question because it's true. Uh Anivva in
the chat said, you know, asking what
supports do you have or desire to have
post treatment is so important. And so
great call out there. Um I know that you
have limited time in your schedule, but
please feel free to stick around. Our
next part that we're working on now is
harm reduction and quality improvement
framework. And so the work group that uh
that actually invited you here today is
going to be talking a little bit about
their next sprint. And so if you do have
time, we would love for you to stick
around and offer insights if you see
anything. Again, knowing that if you do
need to jump off, we completely
understand and you can always just use
that that red lead button up there too.
So, but thank you so much Dr. Pitzky for
being here with us today and Danielle
for inviting him too. So, thank you all.
So, on our next we've been working with
on the intersectional work groups. This
is our harm reduction and quality
improvement framework. Uh and so just to
kind of recap everybody if you haven't
been here before, we decided to do a
little bit of work regarding this around
our responsibilities. So this work
group's responsibility is to create a
reporting framework and to create a harm
reduction quality improvement framework
and also to create a core and extended
data set framework. And so the three
work groups that got created from that
is a care pathway and safety work group,
a participant experience and fit work
group, and a data and reporting
architecture work group. And so from our
last meeting, got to appreciate all of
the work that they've done. Uh because
there's a lot of guiding principles that
we're working with and through on this.
Um the idea is that anything that we're
doing with the New Mexico model, it's a
patient centered throughout. So when
we're capturing data, we want to make
sure that it is all the way through
we're focusing on the patient. Um we've
spoken about using non-violent
communications, really focusing on
feelings and needs. Uh collecting once
uh and not and using it many times so
that we don't burden our patients with
ongoing just repetitive and duplicative
work. Uh capture at the point of care by
the best physician person. So this is
kind of a shared responsibility. So it
doesn't all fall onto one person.
Minimize the client burden through
compassionate timing. So maybe we don't
frontload everything, but maybe and we
don't backload everything, but how do we
best capture that data through that
whole process? Collect only what you're
going to act on. Uh it's nice to collect
a lot of things, but we need to make
sure that the data that we do collect is
something that we can use and take
action with. Uh this is uh utilizing
this medicine is hard to describe. So
honor the ineffable. So a lot of times
you'll need to have some yes and nos and
a lot of times you'll have to have a lot
of open-ended so that we can capture
both of those things. U
capturing cultural and spiritual
humility and making it feel human and
not clinical. So those are kind of a lot
of the frameworks that we've been
working through. Um their last sprint,
the workg group had come up with this
kind of a phase and flow system about
what information is captured and
reported at those different times. I
won't read it all. I'm leaving it on the
screen for you to be able to look at.
Danielle presented this last time. So
again, that was in the record, but just
wanted to bring everybody's focus back
to the previous sprint and what was uh
what was brought as a best practice to
this workg group. And so today we'll be
talking a lot about the harm reduction
and quality improvement framework uh
from these three workg groupoups. And so
at this time this is what I would love
to be able to turn over to anybody from
the work groups. Danielle, I know that
you had a little bit of Yes. Exactly.
This is why I was like, save the time
for you, Gregory, so that that way you
can expand and elaborate on this during
this time. Um, and especially because
like I said, if Dr. Blisk is still here,
you have a little bit of time to maybe
have some response on that as well. So,
whomever from the work groups would like
to report out, uh, go ahead and raise
your hand and we'll go ahead and unmute
your mic as well.
Oh, and yeah, there we go. James,
hello everyone. So, there was a large
focus here on that harm reduction
strategies and we kind of focused in
with the various groups on uh the piece
that I put together was trying to
complement Danielle's amazing work that
she had done. So with my uh harm
reduction strategies, what I what I was
thinking was you know again focusing on
the three areas that was in the previous
slide the preparatory uh what's was
actually happening dur during the
administration session um you know
session time and then afterwards right
that integration piece that we always
talk about um and how important that is
um and so one of the things if we go
through a few of these is preparatory
strategies would be knowledge seeking
what's the mindset That's again sentence
setting safety and then body uh was
mentioned there. Um during the session
we would had emotional support. um you
know actually what else is going on
during that administration session music
other things um there's a lot of
different therap
and then what about modifying the
environment right that's one of the big
things that's that's during that
administration session that was brought
up and then at the very end we had
factors that are influencing you know
integration is there outside factors
like Dr. Pinsky said, "Is there inside
factors in the house?" Uh, motivation
for use. You know, why was this person?
What was their intention? Right? I think
we need to focus back on the intention
and preparatory. Um, and then social
setting is big and then dosing as well.
And then as as well as like maybe
phenotype or something else is like
actually what is that dose and what was
it, you know, and and so I think that
was a big harm reduction uh three key
categories. there's a lot of barriers
and challenges to be successful in this
group to be for harm reduction. I think
we need to look at those barriers and
challenges um and that was brought up um
and other things that help maybe help
with harm reduction practices to help
with the the psychedelic or psycho
therapeutic effect of it like
journaling, meditation, uh creative
expression, uh uh physical practices,
what are they doing there? Um and some
of the barriers or challenges that we
were looking at were uh dose
understanding, dose conversion, having
to create qualified uh permites. That's
a big thing is is how are we going to
create and have qualified permites
um duration of effectiveness intensity
safety concerns again that poly
substance drug interactions and then
dropouts. Um and so that was the big
focus Dan that we had put and everybody
that we kind of put together to start.
So I think this is again a starting
point um to build back on Danielle's
previous work of where you know she was
kind of pointing us this way which was
amazing and then what are those
practical implications I think that's
where we kind of focus back on again is
those implications
um you know not just with psilocybin but
with with that integration piece and how
does that going to affect the person
long term um thank you so much I'll be
quiet I'll let Greg or or Danielle talk
or anybody else from the
Thank you, James. Appreciate that
update. Margaret,
>> uh, super unprepared today. um
[laughter]
I've been so buried in all that training
and education stuff which ultimately
folds into this. But it's um a couple
things that I wanted to touch on that we
have in the list like the
uh
sorry as I'm reading out loud. Um, we
touched on the therapeutic alliance and
I think that's something that we need to
like dig dig deeper into to find out
what um instrumentation and process we
can we can define in our core set of
like preparatory
um uh instrumentation to define. But one
of the interesting things that I wanted
to touch on here is because New Mexico
is very unique in that it is using whole
mushrooms and a lot of studies don't use
whole mushrooms
and we just passed our um propagation
and um testing
rules. So those laws are you know all
but defined inside that we have a
process in our program where we harvest
a lot combine that into a homogenized
lot and from that homogenized lot we do
testing with a that that includes
um
uh deviation. Right? So you have to be
inside a standard deviation for your lot
to pass [clears throat] and then you
create product lots. So we have
extremely
precise
data. We will have extremely precise
data on the whole mushroom that is being
given as a dose.
From that we will be in that in that
testing panel we test for psilocybin
solosin biocyin aruguenason and
norbiocyin
I personally would like to test for
another 20 analytes what for me in my
research one of the most important
things is the non-csychoactives that
support the overall system but what I
think we can start to learn from this
not just from the preparation of the
therapeutic container, but seeing where
it aligns with the chemotype and
structure of the actual medicine because
we are specifically not using solosin or
psilocybin as a synthetic. Um, we are
using this natural compound that is
extremely variant across its expression
in nature.
We are also not tied to one specific
genus or species. We have the language
in our law that allows us to use
psilocybin containing mushrooms. That
means that we can use pinealia
cyanessence. We can use silos
zapidocorum. We can use silosio
centrada. All outside of the standard
data set that we have coming in for
mushrooms. We have the widest range of
possible
um medicines that we can start to track
in alignment with condition
like the individual patients like need
if they're suffering from acute PTSD
or if they're suffering from existential
distress for death and dying like is
there an alignment of unique medication
or I mean in this context like mushroom
chemotype that could feed into
supporting different therapy types
better. Um there's a lot of anecdotal
data and people that have been holding
this work for decades and decades and
decades and decades have knowledge about
like the types of things we do to bring
people into like a safe container and
carry them through and provide the
things and the the way the medicine is
prepared and the way the medicine is
carried. But we are approaching a
possible
data set that can start to define some
of those things. And if it's like I
don't think it's this reductive or
simple, but it's like maybe we just give
people a twoe protocol of tryptophan. If
[laughter]
if if that's the the thing inside the
the chemotype that supports that
specific therapy container, um we can
start to extract. And I don't want to
like be extractive from the medicine.
I'm always going to go back to what that
organic compound is and trust that more
than I am like the extractive measures.
But there are a lot of people that
probably need support that we can find
from this medicine through that deeper
analysis that we have in our capacity.
Um, and that somehow ties to harm
reduction.
>> Great. Thank you very much. Appreciate
it, Gregory. Um, and so I would love to
know from y'all's group, uh, oh,
Danielle just posted, "I am thinking
that the piece we haven't yet worked on
in harm reduction is the feedback loop.
Whether we use open or another system,
our framework covers what gets
collected, from whom, and when, but not
the response mechanism. When the data
surfaces something, what is the
program's responsibility for responding?
Who reviews the findings and on what
timeline? and what does the program own
in terms of making change, adapting,
consent, preparation, training, or
protocols based on what we learned. I'd
like to think about sketching that half
of the loop. Worth naming this piece
because it touches budget, staff time
for review, clinical capacity to
respond, system costs, and involves
facilitators and clinical staff early
since they'll live with it. How do we
scope it deliberately rather than assume
it rides on existing workload? So I'm
not going to be able to answer that full
question because this is exactly what
the work group is. But a lot of that lie
in this workg groupoup meaning that u
the reporting framework that that the
work group has created kind of aligns
out kind of who is responsible for what
and when. And so that data would go into
a data system, which is of course
y'all's next sprint to kind of work on
is what that data system might look
like, what data points are collected,
what data fields are collected, and then
goes into reporting. Um, and then what
we would like to do is that's where
y'all as the work group get to say from
these recommendations that are showing
on the screen as potentials, which ones
do you want to focus on? They can be
prioritized. This doesn't mean to say
that we should do all of them, but we
can't do all of them at once. Do we
focus on something initially
[clears throat]
and then start working to add others or
such, but the idea for this workg group
is to be able to say this is what is
important and we need to have now and
what can we build and extended data set
and then those reports get to come in.
And so the racy committee could be a
committee that we meet and we look at
some of those trends and then see is
this something that is a concern is
there something that we need to work on
because the idea of the continuous
improvement part of this is literally
that. So Danielle I know that doesn't
answer every single part of your
question because a lot of that is
technically what what this workg group
can build and make recommendation in.
And so I feel that you have a lot of
leeway because there isn't anything at
this moment. A lot of this is best
practice. It is not regulatory. So
therefore, it is not something that
would necessarily be baked in in a in a
very restrictive way, but it is
something that we need to consider and
look at for the ongoing health and
longevity of the of the program. Um, and
Gregory, go ahead.
Um, on that note, I'd like to uh extend
a question back to um Roman Pitzky if
he's still here. Um, [clears throat]
I'd like to just hear more about the um
the [clears throat] Syshare system and
who's developing that, what teams
they're working with, what external
tools they're pulling in. And I did
pulled some screenshots of of your your
slides to kind of look at later, but I
really want to see hear what the the
vision is of that and what's needed to
support that and possibly how we can
leverage some of some of that types of
systematic structure in the way that we
develop these tools
um that we will end up using. um
trying to avoid an explicit conflict of
interest, but like I've been working on
something that I hope will will be able
to fold into this um quite nicely. Um
but yeah, if you have some time to share
a little bit more about what size share
is and how we might be able to use it.
>> Sure. Yeah. Um so I I I want to be uh
well I want to say two things. point is
as I was looking at this, one thought
that I had was this is this is really a
great place for implementation science
and for implementation scientists uh
working on this um and and I I think
unfortunately
uh some of that work is only just
beginning but but uh uh but this is
clearly implementation science right um
uh the the other is so sare is really it
it's a way to um to bring the silo data
sets together. And so if there um uh
right now we are we're actually waiting
to hear back about about whether we're
actually going to be able to fund it.
There are two things that people want.
Um, one is a um, one is a repository,
which is let's just collect all of the
potential safety information, you know,
nationwide and put it all into one
common repository and just have all the
data live there. And I think that that's
completely unrealistic right now. Um
because you the the outcomes are so
heterogeneous, the data collection
strategies are so different, the
metadata are so diverse, and you you're
not going to get it all into a sort of a
one ring to rule them all kind of a
format without a lot of consensus
building. Um so and also and also uh
repositories are incredibly expensive.
Um to to host to set up uh I mean I even
even the vaccine monitoring world which
has something more akin to repositories
is still you know still still deals with
these issues right um in terms of uh in
terms of safety data and how do we get
it all into one place. The other thing
that can be done is a registry, which is
much more realistic. And a registry
relies on having a common metadata
dictionary across all of the different
context and settings. And then you can
organize it, make it searchable, and
make it make it so that whoever wants to
look through it and see, okay, well,
this team monitored adverse events in
this way, and that uh state monitored
adverse events in that way, and let me
pull up the data that's useful. So what
Scyshare does is it creates the
landscape and allows you gives you a map
and gives you like the bus tickets to
get to anywhere on that map. Um so
that's that's what sir is. Um
[clears throat] I don't know if if that
if that helps address your needs or not.
I think uh it helps to create a way to
interdigitate the the New Mexico data
with whatever is coming down the pike
from uh from Oregon, from Colorado and
other other states.
>> No, I think that's super helpful. I
think what what you're describing is the
downstream positive [snorts] effect of
whatever it is that we but but we can
utilize share to map backwards to the
other systems that you're already
connected to to see if we can uh dig
into alignment and commonality in um
dictionary mapping if [laughter] if
nothing else.
>> Absolutely. That's one of the that's one
of the uses
>> which is which is actually which is
actually great because the next sprint
that the work groups will be working on
is that kind of data and reporting
architecture when it comes to that. So
there's a you know kind of like a very
large model that could be looked at and
that's why it's defining what is the
core that we need to be able to collect
and some of the core is being defined in
the other work groups as we speak. So
therefore we're kind of doing like
carton horse. So some of the things
we're talking about are just
hypothetical um until those kind of
things get memorialized in uh in in in
the rule and at that time then we will
definitely know what those kind of core
data elements are. At least we're kind
of working in a parallel team on that
and hearing that there might be a great
way to have an intermediary that can
help map across those datas uh that can
kind of line things up across different
states and different research programs
and such is is great news and that's why
we were happy to have open last time
talk a little bit about their program.
Um, one thing I would love to open up
here before we kind of move on to the
next thing is anybody from the anybody
from the entire group that's on would
like to say anything about the quality
uh improvement frameworks or harm
reduction frameworks or things that you
don't see that we have up here on the
screen that needs to be looked at,
considered. Like I said, what are our
blind spots? What did we not see, not
think about?
Uh, and while I'm letting you think
about that a little bit, I do want to go
back and address Kate Hawk. I'm
wondering how the inter session workg
groupoups get set up. I don't need to
get on everything, but would like to
understand the process and Gregory said
that's why I said careful what you ask
for. So, um, I know Kate, keep an eye on
the chat because the individuals that
are running those three work groups will
drop their uh, emails into the chat. So
like Gregory and James and Danielle and
so you can definitely reach out to them
to say hey when when are we kind of
working on some of that stuff for the
the next sprint. So
and uh James Brown said next work group
meeting focus outcome monitoring the
feedback loop uh research data points
process ideas feedback uh quality
aggregation of everything improvement
and other pies needed. Absolutely.
Right.
And yeah, James Kate and there's
Danielle's email in the the chat there
for you.
And this is um kind of real quick what
kind of looks at this is not anything in
the consensus uh at all, but this is
just recommendations that we've been
looking at for work group three for the
next sprint, which is a core and data
core and extended data set. So there are
certain pieces of data that can be
collected. The work group three is
really going to be focusing on what are
the things from this that make sense in
the core and what makes sense in the um
and the extended data set. And then of
course uh the other two work groups fit
in with that as well because the idea is
they have to be able to define in the
data how this gets collected, how this
gets entered into data and and
translated from the real world into
something that can be stored, reported,
aggregated, those kind of things. So
together these big groups here will be
working on those things on the next
sprint. And as you notice that our next
uh workg group, our next committee
meeting will be here on August 7th. And
so we'll hear more from the inter
session work groups on those kinds of
things at that time. Um Gregory, go
ahead.
Um, just since we're um kind of up
against the end of the wall here, I
wanted to circle back with you on how we
can
kind of start to frame [snorts] this
into a work back and figure out what our
kind of like recommendation deadline is.
Um, just through watching the last two
committees go through the process of
translating the recommendation into
rules language, I want to be better
[clears throat] prepared as we continue
to learn that process and um start to
understand how we can more effectively
pull all of this together when it's time
to send it back to the
department as or or back to the board to
go to the department. and what type of
presentation
um would be most effective. I think that
this is going to be, you know, to the
uninitiated, it's going to look like a
very massive and unnauseating
unsurmountable amount of like data
points that are going to have this
massive effect on people's experience
and in resistance to sharing data and
all that. But it's like we have we I
think we do have the tools uh available
to us to make it simple in a way. And so
I just want to see how we can start to
aim for that target and when we need to
start, you know, writing things in a
present in in a recommendation manner.
Um just kind of thoughts based on this
week's fun drama.
>> Sure. So, um, the I I'll speak on my
behalf personally and then I would love
for anybody on the DO side to be able to
either tell me that I'm completely off
my mark or or something else is here.
So, uh, what I'm about to say, please
understand it is not the the beall
endall gospel on this. So, just let's
just keep it on that. So, first I would
like to say that um our our kind of work
group that we've been trying to get to
this point is that um we we looked at
August 7th as the date for the work
groups to come back to this this
committee and kind of make that
presentation that here's what we're
looking at for the core extended data
set framework. um knowing that may not
be realistic. That's the reason why I
also held the September 11th date on the
calendar. So that August 7th might be
like a little bit of like here's the
draft idea and let people kind of talk
about it. If there isn't anything on the
August 7th meeting for the data sets,
then it'll probably be very difficult to
have any kind of conversation on that.
Um so we do want to kind of get to that
point. I say September 11th because
again this is not necessarily I mean in
in in the regulations will be certain
data elements that are required because
they're already working on that when it
comes to the propagation that's already
been passed and then also in education
and training and things like there are
data elements that they've talked about
as well. So we'll have to rely on those
but again uh keeping an eye on what
they're making the recommendation on can
help inform this work as well. So
September 11th takes us real close
because then we have October, November,
and December when the program gets um uh
turned on basically in January of 2027.
There must be something in place at
least from a very basic core data set on
that. So that would be our timeline
we're running up against. So therefore,
I'm going to also say I don't believe
that needs to go through necessarily the
regulatory hearing framework because
this is more on the data side. But
that's where I said now I'm going to
turn it over to the DOH team to say
everything I said was not true and so
they can come back and and advise me
what I just said was was on track or not
track or whatever. So
>> thank you Dan. uh and actually you're
very much on track and one of the points
I really want to emphasize here is there
already is within the recommendations
and the plans that the that people will
or that the providers at various levels
and all of that will have to report data
through the online reporting system that
we're going to be establishing. the the
full details of that actually is going
to be a part of some of the best
practices because remember um patients
are always going to have that ability to
opt out. So we can't require them to do
so and um and and in doing that that
means that we set up the programs we
have that and then it's in many ways
whether you want to think of it as opt
out or opt in either way it will be up
to in the long run the patient to make
that determination. So this doesn't
actually fit within that same regulatory
framework and so we don't have to go
through all of those processes. The
other thing that that actually allows is
it also allows that other organizations
potentially who are interested in doing
research who have also gotten uh um you
know approval through um through their
different processes and then got then
reviewed in part by this committee and
agreed upon. And that could be some of
the other existing ones which we've
talked about before open and some of the
other sort of situation or uh other
research um uh elements and
organizations that are really working
towards this. And so with regard to that
um we can we can go ahead and move
forward. Um and this timeline that Dan
outlined actually fits in very well with
that. And James, it's actually the
points are really just about when is a
patient starting service, you know, when
would they be finishing? It's really
very basic on it because again, any of
that kind of data being collected, the
patients have to agree upon. And so it
doesn't need to be defined within the
regulatory. Sorry, I'm also reading out
of the chat. My apologies on it if I
confused anyone who's not seeing the
chat right away, but um I just want to
just outline that. So this is really
about what what this group really comes
on up with is what we start moving
forward with. Now one thing that I do
want to just be clear about is also
remember a lot of it is also about
resources you know and so if we don't
have the resources for example to do the
analysis and to do uh you know the I
mean we're trying to do the data
collecting in ways that'll be online so
it minimizes the requirements from that
standpoint of like time and effort and
those things but analysis also takes a
lot of time so remember if you have
something like this just the slide
that's up right now about the reporting
architecture. Think about how many data
points there are in this or how many
actually extend out from it. So, we have
to really think about that aspect as
well because while it would be great to
get all of the information possible, one
that's just not really going to be
possible um because people aren't going
to sit down for the time to complete
that kind of a survey or information,
but second about how much time it's
going to take to analyze. It doesn't do
us a lot of good to collect data that
never gets used because lack of analysis
and and it becomes a waste of time.
quite frankly for the patients, the
providers at the different levels, all
of that. So we need to make sure to keep
that in mind. And so just remember those
parts as we move forward in the next
steps. We want to have great data
collection, but data collection itself
is only the beginning. We also need to
have uh great analysis and then and
Heneifeha actually I believe yes
Heneifeha made a comment about what the
FE feedback loop is. So that has to be a
part of this as well because it's also
great to analyze it but then if it never
gets out to anybody and and utilize then
there again what have we done and so
think about those aspects of it as we
move forward. I hope I know that was a
little longer than an explanation than
you probably needed or wanted but um you
know that's kind of the the main points
I would say to think about as we move
forward over these next couple of
months. Yeah,
>> that is perfect. No, thank you because
that's exactly where we need to come
from because like I said, this is kind
of like the the shopping list of
everything that we could possibly look
at. And the idea of of the work groups
is to really come back and say with just
everything that Dominic has mentioned
that we need to be mindful number one of
our patients, we need to be mindful of
our programs. We need to be mindful of
the team on that. Um however there are
certain things that we need to make sure
for safety quality improvements and
things that we need to look at making
sure that we are focused on so that's
where the balance will come in from the
team. So that's why I said it's like
here's like everything that could be
possibly looked at. What are the things
that the team has said? This is kind of
the the non-negotiables we have to have
and it will not be all of this. This is
just like I said ideas to think about.
Um so really that's what it comes down
to. So for the August 7th meeting it
really is to say this is it. This is
this is it. And then we can have that
conversation to say too much, too
little, whatever. And from a
recommendation standpoint, still have
the 11th then to come back and come to
consensus as well. But that I hope that
kind of really helped. And again, it may
not have helped at all. may have made
more confusing, but I hope it did help
to some degree.
>> Yeah, that helps a lot. And just one
more kind of uh back to the department.
Um, I know that the DO and a lot of
government organizations have very
careful steps in how they can implement
um, AI
tools. Um, in the idea that like these
massive data sets can be translated into
usable research
and public data hopefully. Um do we know
if the department is
uh has any guidelines on how that can be
utilized in software? Um I would imagine
there will be requirements for sock 2
and ISO standards and those can be like
all defined as we like a lot of that
stuff is like shifting significantly in
the industry as we move into 2027. But
uh just wondering if there's like goals
or guidelines or concerns that they have
from the data implementation
side of things as we move into the part
of the year where those tools need to be
like getting up and running.
>> Thank you, Greg. That's a a great
question. and uh and actually the
department does have um some
restrictions with with regard to the use
of AI due to some security issues,
security concerns that are going on.
Those are actually at this time uh
regularly evolving. So when we get to
that point, we'll need to see what all
of the updates are. Right now, honestly,
it is very limited because of those
security concerns, especially when it
comes to information about patient data
and research. And so, um, as we get a
little closer to that, we'll get updates
as far as what is allowed, what is not,
and be able to work as far as
implementing them.
>> Thank you. And I just wanted to put one
more reminder up that our next meeting
date is on August 7th at which time uh
if the work groups will be able to kind
of bring back again this just this exact
what we talked about this kind of
concept of a core data set. Um and that
way these are the things that uh we
definitely need to make sure that the
data is gathering and collecting and
reporting and analyzing and feedback
loop and all those kind of things to it.
So that would be kind of our next sprint
from now until uh one month from now. Um
and I just appreciate everybody's time
here. So I know that some people might
be jumping off a little bit soon here.
So it's not the end of the meeting. It's
time for public comment. But I did want
to just make sure that you know that
also right after this meeting at 1:00.
Please make sure that you come to Dr.
Leman's end of life meeting. And there
are additional meetings next week on the
13th on patient quality. uh dosage is on
the July 14th and training and
education's on the 17th and that's at
1:00 and we'll also have another board
meeting on the 17th at 9:00. So please
put those on your calendar, register for
them at the uh psilocybin advisory board
links and we'll jump into the chat here
in a little bit. Uh and at this point um
we'll go ahead and leave the last few
minutes for anybody that would have any
kind of public comment. Again, public
comment is always open mic. three
minutes of your time. Um, feel free to
be able to share anything that we didn't
get to talk about or any topic that
relates to research and continuous
improvement.
And in order to speak, just make sure
that you use your hand feature in the uh
teams and that way you can then be able
to be unmuted to speak.
Of course, you can always drop anything
into the chat. Uh if you do have
anything that you do want to be added to
the public record uh after the meeting,
you can always send it to the
medical.silocybin
at duhnm.gov
website there as well. Uh just went into
the chat there too. Perfect.
And again because educator I'll give
some wait time just in case people are
still considering to raise their hand.
And if not that's okay. I completely
understand. I appreciate everybody's
time today here. Uh if you are spending
the rest of your day enjoying it getting
into the weekend, thank you very much. I
appreciate you being here and otherwise
have a great weekend. We'll see you all
the next time we have a meeting
together.
>> Thank you everybody on behalf of the
department. We appreciate everybody
being here and contributing. Thank you.
Have a great weekend.
>> Thank you Dr. Biski for being here. Have
a great one. Thank you team from DO and
everybody that came to the meeting
today. Appreciate you being
There we go. Got it.